<topic template="Default" lasteditedby="David" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">SRV Files - Overview</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword translate="true">SRV Files</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">SRV Files - Overview</text></para>
    </header>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">The data files accepted by Walls are simple script-like text files with the default extension SRV. &#160;If you have written programs before, you can think of them as source files to be interpreted during a Walls </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Compilation" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">compilation</link><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">. &#160;The mostly &quot;free-form&quot; style, where keywords specify the meaning of data, has two main advantages. &#160;First, the files can resemble what is actually written in field books, so they are easy to proofread and largely self-explanatory. Second, it&apos;s easy to extend the format to handle new data types while still keeping old data files compatible. Unlike a proprietary database that requires a specific program for interpretation, the files can be safely archived. </text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">There are a few disadvantages as well. The choice of ordinary text as the program&apos;s native data format brings us long-term flexibility with a slight ease-of-use penalty. &#160;A new user cannot immediately begin entering data without becoming familiar with at least a few features of the script format. &#160;Also, data entry errors are detected during compilation, not as they are being keyed in. &#160;Since syntax checking is quite thorough in Walls, a large chunk of freshly entered data may require a few stops and restarts before it cleanly compiles. When compilation is halted this way, an appropriate message is displayed and the questionable text pops up in an editor window. </text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Below is a small survey (10 shots) as it would appear in a Walls editor window. &#160;Note that comments are prefixed with a semicolon. &#160;The grid lines in this window appear because the option to display tab characters as vertical lines is turned on. &#160;The Walls editor makes it very easy to use tabs to separate line items. &#160;(See </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Survey_Text_Editor" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Survey Text Editor</link><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">.) </text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><image src="HACK.bmp" scale="100.00%" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;"></image></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Most SRV files are </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">small in size</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true"> -- typed in by the surveyors themselves either during or immediately after an expedition. &#160;A typical file will consist of data obtained by one team on one surveying trip. &#160;It is the purpose of the </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="project_script_file" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">project script</link><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true"> (WPJ file) to link the possibly numerous SRV data files together in a way that they are easily managed and operated on. &#160;Except for possible future corrections, the data files themselves should</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">&#32;</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">not</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">&#32;</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">require revision once they are created and proofread.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Because of the need to handle preexisting data, the SRV format also supports the practice of lumping everything, even multiple unconnected caves, into one large text file. &#160;My preference, however, is to package a </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">project</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true"> -- a collection of many SRV files and one or more WPJ files -- into one ZIP archive for transport and backup.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">General Description</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:324px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">The files are ordinary text (actually ANSI, a superset of ASCII) and can be created with the Walls built-in editor or with most other text editors,</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-weight:bold; color:#000000;" translate="true">&#32;</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">including Windows Notepad. &#160;During compilation, the program reads a file line-by-line while recognizing the semicolon character as a comment prefix. &#160;Except for the first whole-line comment, which Walls uses as the default title when the file is added to a project via the &quot;browse&quot; feature, anything on a line following a semicolon is ignored. &#160;Blank lines are also ignored.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:324px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Each line is read as a sequence of </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">tokens</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true"> (strings of displayable characters), where the number of spaces and tab characters between tokens is irrelevant. &#160;Except for certain text data, such as station and </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="segment_attributes" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">segment</link><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true"> names, the case (upper or lower) of characters in a token doesn&apos;t matter. &#160;During compilation, if Walls encounters something it doesn&apos;t like, it displays an error message and highlights the offending line in an editor window.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:324px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:324px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">You&apos;ll discover that the program is quite strict in deciding what numeric forms are reasonable. &#160;For example, not only will it reject</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-weight:bold; color:#000000;" translate="true">&#32;</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">negative distances and azimuths, but an entry like &quot;+10&quot; for anything but an inclination or above-station height will also trigger an error message. &#160;Why? &#160;Because entering measurements out of order is a very common mistake.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Special lines, called </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">directives, </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">have their first token prefixed with a pound sign (e.g., #Units, #Segment, #Prefix, etc.) and are used to specify such things as station and vector attributes, measurement units, and measurement column order. &#160;Other lines in the file define </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">vectors</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-weight:bold; color:#000000;" translate="true">&#32;</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">between pairs of named stations. &#160;Ordinarily, these are the survey &quot;shots&quot; that resemble data lines in field books.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">The range of measurement units now supported by the SRV format is much larger than it once was, but of course it still won&apos;t satisfy everyone. &#160;A complex format takes longer to describe and is harder to export to other programs. &#160;Already, it&apos;s not easy gathering data that&apos;s sufficiently diverse for testing purposes. &#160;For this reason I&apos;ve tried to avoid adding features until they are actually needed for current projects. &#160;Nonetheless, I will continue to make changes to the format -- hopefully in a way that keeps old data files compatible.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
  </body>
</topic>
