<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" lasteditedby="David" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Editing Records</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Editing Records</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Selecting Point Features for Editing</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">As illustrated in the </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Getting_Started" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Getting Started</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> topic, you can select records for editing in any of several different ways. For example, while exploring the map you can right-click a displayed symbol and select the topmost option from a pop-up context menu. Another way is to click a toolbar icon (white arrow with small rectangle) and left-drag a rectangle enclosing the points of interest. There&apos;s also a text search dialog (accessed via the binocular toolbar icon) where you can search attribute fields for text using a variety of options. Finally you can select multiple records by selecting rows in a </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Getting_Started" anchor="Table_View" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">table view</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> and choosing either &quot;Open as selected points&quot; or &quot;Add to selected points&quot; from the table&apos;s context menu.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">With all these methods, matching points are displayed in the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Selected Points</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> window where they can be individually examined. The names (labels) of selected points appear alphabetically in a tree diagram on the left side, their parent branches indicating the corresponding layers:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="Selection1.jpg" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Here you can directly edit both the location and attribute fields of a feature highlighted in the tree. Only when you move away from a feature, say by selecting a different tree branch, are changes committed to files. Until then, the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Reset Attr</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button (at bottom of window) and the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Undo Reloc</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button (at top-right) let you undo any edits.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Like the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Layers</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> window, the</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> Selected Points</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> window is resizable and can stay open while you perform other operations, such as &#160;panning and zooming the map view. For example, when a feature is highlighted in this window you might want to change its location to a recognizable place on the map. You can do this by repositioning the view as necessary and right-clicking the map at the desired new location:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="Pseudosink.jpg" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Besides point relocation, the pop-up menu offers the choice of creating a new point with attributes initialized to have the same values as the highlighted point. To create a new point with blank attribute values, highlight a root of the tree (the shapefile&apos;s title) before right-clicking on the map.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">After adding or relocating a point visually, you may want to adjust the resulting location via the edit boxes at the top of the window. When you make changes in those boxes, however, you&apos;ll need to click the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Relocate</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button for the changes to take effect. Note that as long as you stay positioned at a point, successive relocations can be undone in reverse sequence via the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Undo Reloc</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Instead of directly editing the individual coordinate fields, you&apos;ll often find it more efficient to transfer, with a single paste operation, a pair of coordinates copied from another source. This could from another shapefile record in the project, from the map view&apos;s Center on Point dialog, or directly from a web mapping application. (See </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Getting_Started" anchor="Web_Mapping" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">examples</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.) The copy/paste options are selections in the right-click context menu for a highlighted tree item as shown below. In this example the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Paste coordinates</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> selection is disabled (grayed) because the program notices that the Windows clipboard doesn&apos;t contain what it would recognize as a valid coordinate pair. What it looks for and accepts are a variety of common formats used for a pair of geographical coordinates, including Lat/Long forms that aren&apos;t ordinarily displayed, such as as N 30° 25&apos; 30.5&quot;, W 97 15&apos; 2&quot; or simply 30 25 30.5 -97 15 2.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="Pt_context.png" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><anchor id="Editing_memos" styleclass="Normal"></anchor></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Editing Memo Field Content </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Both in the Selected Points window (as shown above) and in a table view, memo fields appear as pushbuttons followed, possibly, by a fragment of text representing the first portion of the memo&apos;s content. In the Selected Points right panel there is space for a single indicator just left of the button. It&apos;s either a tilde (~) indicating presence of a set of linked image files, an asterisk indicating a non-empty text memo, or a blank if the field is empty. If it&apos;s a tilde, left-clicking the button opens the </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Getting_Started" anchor="Memo_links" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">image preview</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> window. When there&apos;s no tilde, or if you </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">right</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">-click the button, the text editor window opens to display the field&apos;s content.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="Editor_context_menu.png" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">While relatively basic in capability, the editor does allow switching between plain text and rich text formats, the latter being compatible with programs like WordPad and Microsoft Word. It also has a </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Save to file</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> function that creates a file with the appropriate extension -- either txt or rtf. The suggested output file name in the save dialog will be of the form &quot;Texas Public Caves_#2_REPORT-Bracken Bat Cave.rtf.&quot; Note that the shapefile name, record number, field name, and record label is represented in this name, which of course you can change.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">When a database has multiple contributors the maintainer might need to compare two different versions of a long report. The program currently doesn&apos;t support more than one open editor window, but for such comparisons this would be of limited value anyway. Instead we have the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Compare with last saved</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> function. When enabled it launches a compare/merge program with the contents of two memo fields displayed side-by-side: the current memo at left and the</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true"> last saved</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> memo at right. The launch operation involves the creation, without prompting, of a file to store the current memo using the above naming convention. The compare program (the specific one used being a preference setting) will then highlight any differences. It might also allow you to edit either side, in which case you can load the result into either memo field using the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Replace with file</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> option.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Options related to the editor, such as colors, type styles, and initial opening mode can be set in the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Text Editor Preferences</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> dialog accessed via the program&apos;s main menu (Preferences | Text editor preferences). That dialog contains a </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Text compare program: Options</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button that lets you specify which program, if any, is available for comparing memo text. The program used by default, if it&apos;s installed, is the open source </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="weblink" href="http://winmerge.org/" target="_blank" styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">WinMerge</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. For more details on this option, see </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Comparing_Memo_Field_Text" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Comparing Memo Field Text</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Creating an Image Memo</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Finally, note the button labeled </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Image Mode</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> at the editor window&apos;s lower left. It&apos;s enabled when an empty memo (or one that already contains image links) is first opened. Its purpose is to the replace the editor window with an empty </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Getting_Started" anchor="Memo_links" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Image Viewer</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> window, one with an entirely different interface. From the Windows file manager you can drag and drop (or copy and paste) image files to this window. There are also context menu options for adding information such as titles and captions.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">A memo with image links contains standard text, but it&apos;s formatted a special way, such that when the memo&apos;s button is left-clicked the thumbnail-style viewer will open instead of the editor. (If the text editor happens to be open with a different memo, it won&apos;t be affected.) To ascertain the simple format we use for image memos,</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true"> right-click</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> the memo&apos;s button to view or edit the text directly. Some types of changes, such as fixing a misspelled photographer&apos;s name, might be easier to perform while in editor mode using the search-and-replace function.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Editing Attributes in a Table View</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Opening a table view of all or part of a shapefile makes in-place editing of field values possible. It&apos;s the only way, currently, to edit shapefiles that aren&apos;t of type 2D point. One must be careful with table edits, however, since it&apos;s easy to make changes that can&apos;t be undone. Unlike the Selected Points form, moving away from a cell will commit the change. For this reason, the table&apos;s window has a checkbox to enable editing. (If you find the checkbox disabled, you&apos;ll first need right-click the shapefile&apos;s title in the Layers window and select </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Allow editing this file</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.)</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">When browsing the attributes of a 2D point shapefile, you&apos;ll often find it convenient to select several rows, right-click on one of them, and choose either </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Open as Selected Point(s)</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> or </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Add to Selected Points</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. You&apos;ll then be able to use the Selected Points dialog to modify the assigned coordinates. Any special attribute fields that may exist (coordinates, timestamps, etc.) will appear in both table and form views, but only as grayed text. Such fields are never directly edited.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Record Deletion vs. Removal</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Note the &quot;Delete record&quot; option in the above context menu. It&apos;s also present in a table view&apos;s context menu. This operation </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">flags</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> the selected records in a standard way so that thereafter programs will ignore them. By default, WallsMap will skip deleted records when exporting shapefiles. In a table view it&apos;s possible to </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Reload</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> the table content so that the deleted records are visible as rows with asterisk prefixes. Also, the menu option </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">View</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> | </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Select Edited features</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> can open deleted points in the Selected Points window. Whenever deleted records are visible they can be selectively </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">undeleted</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">To remove a record from a database using the </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Submitting_a_Shapefile_Update" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Compare with other layers</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> function, one does </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">not</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> delete the record in the shapefile being edited. The convention this program has adopted for scheduling a removal is to simply edit the label field, inserting an asterisk (*) as the first character. Once the shapefile is received and processed by the primary database manager,</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> the record will be gone from the master shapefile and its key permanently retired.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Transferring Coordinates from One Point to Another</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">A quick way to relocate a point to the position of another point is by right-clicking a tree item in the Selected Points window and choosing </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Copy coordinates</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> or </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Paste coordinates</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> from the pop-up menu. The copy operation, when creating text for the Windows clipboard, uses the format you&apos;ve set for the location edit boxes, such as Lat/Long and NAD83. The paste operation simply inserts the clipboard&apos;s text into the edit boxes without regard for coordinate system and datum setting. The paste isn&apos;t allowed, however, if the program doesn&apos;t recognize the text as a pair of numbers. After a paste, you can either click the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Relocate</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button to actually move the point and update the map view, or click the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Reset Loc</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> button to undo the paste.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Special Case: Testing Datum Assumptions</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Using the coordinate copy/paste operation you can test for common datum errors with just a few mouse clicks. For example, if you suspect that a NAD27 UTM GPS reading was mistakenly assumed to be WGS84 (or equivalently NAD83) when it was stored in the shapefile, perform the following steps while the point is highlighted in the Selected Points window:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <list id="1" type="ul" listtype="bullet" formatstring="&#183;" format-charset="SYMBOL_CHARSET" levelreset="true" legalstyle="false" startfrom="1" styleclass="Normal" style="font-family:Symbol; font-size:11pt; color:#000000;">
      <li styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">Set the format for the location edit boxes to the questionable datum and associated coordinate type --</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> NAD83 and UTM in this example.</text></li>
      <li styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Right-click the point&apos;s label in the window&apos;s left panel and select </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Copy coordinates.</text></li>
      <li styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Change the datum setting for the edit boxes to the other possibility (NAD27) and perform a </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Paste coordinates</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> operation.</text></li>
      <li styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">Click</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Relocate</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> button (knowing that you can undo the relocation).</text></li>
    </list>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">As you click </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Relocate</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, examine the map view. If the feature&apos;s marker moves to a place you like better, you may have corrected a set of UTM coordinates for which WGS84 was wrongly assumed. In Central Texas the placemark will have shifted </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">205</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> meters north and </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">35</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> meters west. Here you&apos;re checking the possibility that UTM coordinates were tagged with the wrong datum. Perhaps surprisingly, the size of the location shift is different when testing a datum assigned to Lat/Long coordinates. For locations in Central Texas, changing a Lat/Long datum from NAD83 to NAD27 will shift the placemark </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">25</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> meters north and </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">30</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> meters west. Of course, with either coordinate type, correcting a mistaken NAD27 assumption will produce a shift in the opposite direction. When neither the original coordinate type or the &quot;direction&quot; of the suspected datum error is known, you may want to test all four possibilities while examining the map&apos;s imagery.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
  </body>
</topic>
