<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" lasteditedby="David" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Exporting Shapefiles from TSS2000.MDB</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Exporting Shapefiles from TSS2000.MDB</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="TSS-Export.png" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Upon startup, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS-Export</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> looks for a Microsoft Access database named TSS2000.MDB in its own folder. If the file is found it automatically scans the main table component, TSSTEX, to accumulate statistics for display. (The user can also switch to a different database at any time after startup.) The database must have a table named TSSTEX with a recognizable set of fields.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">To give you control over the type of attribute tables your shapefiles will contain, the program&apos;s dialog has a drop-down listbox labeled &quot;Template&quot;. It might offer a selection of more than one </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">attribute template</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> (a text file with extension .shpdef) that specify the names and types of source and destination fields. If you&apos;re targeting WallsMap and want to create a shapefile suitable for round-tripping, you should make sure that </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">All_Data-TSS</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> is selected before clicking the &quot;Export&quot; button. Although it was once necessary to be able to exclude specific fields (such as memos) when satisfying data requests, there&apos;s now little reason to use an alternate template since WallsMap has more flexible export capabilities.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Note that there are five feature type categories, the definitions of which are listed under </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Karst_Feature_Categories" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Karst Feature Categories</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. During each export operation, a single shapefile is produced containing a mixture of feature types depending on the checked state of five dialog boxes. Our current practice is to produce at least six shapefiles for a WallsMap project named </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS_Data</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">: </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS Caves.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS Shelters.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS Springs.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS Sinks.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS Other.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, and </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS All_Types.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. The last one, containing everything, serves as a backup and is not meant to be edited when the project is worked on by contributors. We can, however, use it to explore a table view of the entire database.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The non-overlapping feature categories (as determined by field TYPE in the database) are useful for producing map layers with different symbols, and whose visibility can easily be toggled on and off. To display with separate symbols all mapped features and/or all records with fauna lists, we might also choose to export two additional shapefiles: </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS Maps.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> and </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS TexBio.shp</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> (note corresponding checkboxes). The only problem with this is that if you&apos;re editing records (especially locations), the presence of those layers might cause confusion if they&apos;re not also kept up-to-date.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Running </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS-Export</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> is a quick way to obtain feature counts, displayed in red in the dialog window. The counts in parentheses for &quot;unlocated&quot; features &#160;with empty coordinate fields, where usually little more than a county name is known. (Actually there are a few records with &quot;Unknown&quot; in the COUNTY field, these being the only records with missing TSS IDs). To include those records in an exported shapefile we must check the &quot;Include Unlocated&quot; box and click the button beside it to specify a suitable, hopefully recognizable location that the exporter can assign. Those features can then be easily selected and examined in a GIS project. The Lat/Long (NAD83) locations we&apos;re currently using for the TSS_Data project, situated in the SE corner of New Mexico, are as follows:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">TSS Caves: (32.4,103.7), TSS Shelters: (32.4,-103.5), TSS Springs: (32.2,-103.9), TSS Sinks: (32.2,-103.7), TSS Other: 32.2,-103.5), TSS All_Types: (32.4,-103.9), TSS Maps: (32.4,-103.3), and TSS TexBio: (32.2,-103.3).</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Besides being prominent on the map (see image under </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="TSS_Database_Overview" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Database Overview)</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, the unlocated features are easily recognized in a table view sorted on one of the coordinates. The exporter can also produce UTM shapefiles for county or regional projects. (Although GIS programs, including WallsMap, can automatically convert between coordinate systems when a shapefile is loaded, it might be slightly more efficient to avoid this conversion). For these shapefiles it&apos;s better to choose a different place to park unlocated items, perhaps just outside the county line. The convention, so far, has been to place all unlocated feature types in these projects at the same point.</text></para>
  </body>
</topic>
