<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" lasteditedby="David" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Google Earth (KML) Launch Options</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Google Earth (KML) Launch Options</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="KML_options.png" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The Range setting is the approximate minimum width of the view, in meters, when the KML file is first opened by Google Earth, or selected in the GE side panel. If there are multiple point features in the file, all of their placemarks should initially occupy about two thirds of either this range or whatever larger one is required for complete coverage. When a single feature of the set is selected in the side panel, the view should zoom to the specified range, with the feature centered and seen from a point directly above it. That is, you should </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">not</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> see a tilted, or oblique view of the ground.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">To prevent tilting of the view from occurring when zooming with the mouse, however, you may need to open Google Earth&apos;s Tools | Options | Navigation dialog and specify </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Do not automatically tilt when zooming</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The KML file will contain one of the specified placemark symbol URLs, the particular one used depending on whether or not multiple points are being exported. This could be made more flexible, but at least having two separate icons allows us to fly to a temporary point that&apos;s easily distinguishable from dozens of &#160;placemarks we may have exported earlier as a group. (The icon for a loaded KML file is also easily changed within GE itself.) The default URLs shown above should work with any KML viewing application as long as the URLs remain valid.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Google Earth, since it runs locally on your computer, should also be able to display custom symbols defined with local file URLs, such as &quot;file://C:/icons/custom.png.&quot; Evidently, that and similar formats aren&apos;t recognized by the program (even if &quot;%20&quot; is substituted for spaces). What does work are ordinary pathnames with forward slashes and no spaces, such as &quot;C:/icons/custom.png.&quot; Of course, any KML file containing such a pathname wouldn&apos;t be suitable for sending to others.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
  </body>
</topic>
