<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" lasteditedby="David" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">TSS Database Overview</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">TSS Database Overview</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="weblink" href="http://www.texasspeleologicalsurvey.org" target="_blank" styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">Texas Speleological Survey</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> karst database was maintained for many years as a </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Microsoft Access</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> database. Because Access by itself was ill-suited for managing geographic information, the TSS adopted a round-tripping process in 2009. This involved exchanging data between an Access table and a WallsMap project named </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS_Data</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. With the database configured as a GIS project, WallsMap could be used for entering new karst features, visually verifying locations, and adding links to documents and image files. In early 2014, a new program feature made it possible to remove Access from the maintenance loop. (See </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Keeping_the_Database_Current" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Keeping the Database Current</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.)</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Each record in the database corresponds to a</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> location</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">&#32;</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">of interest in Texas</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">normally that of an</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> entrance to a cave or similar geologic feature. In some cases, however, we don&apos;t have a good approximation for location. To represent such features in the </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS_Data</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> project we&apos;ve reserved a dummy location in the SE corner of New Mexico. Like other features, their attributes can be searched for and their records edited. </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">When you explore the Texas project you&apos;ll find caves without valid coordinates, but with data in other fields that would narrow the location to a ranch, USGS quadrangle, or maybe to within a few kilometers of something with a known location. The database has a field named COORD_ERR that stores a horizontal location uncertainty in meters. As of now (Oct, 2014) more than half of the records have uncertainty values assigned. </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">About 17% of the more than 13000 features in the database are without approximate coordinates, with </text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">another 2% having uncertainties of at least 500 meters.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">Since it&apos;s our policy not to publicize exact cave locations, we obviously have to limit distribution of the TSS database as a complete GIS project. Authorized users will need to</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> access a password-protected website t</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">o download setup programs for either the database or this TSS edition of WallsMap.</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> Without having to log in each time to check if their versions are current, they can open the WallsMap About box and click on the displayed link. This will open a page showing the two release dates and a link to the protected download site.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">For a summary of the information stored in the database for each karst feature, see </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Field_Definitions" styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">Database Field Descriptions</link><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">TSS_Data Project Layers</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS_Data</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> project is a mixture of several useful geographical datasets, including the essential karst shapefiles.</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> &#160;Its various components (layers) will appear similar to what&apos;s shown below when the Layers/properties window is opened:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="tss_data_layers.png" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">This layer arrangement is what might be chosen by someone making corrections and additions to the database. This is done by editing just the five shapefile layers named </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS Caves</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:normal;" translate="true"> (caves and entrances)</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS Sinks</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:normal;" translate="true"> (sinks and cavities)</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS Shelters</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS Other</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">, and </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS Springs</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. (See </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Karst_Feature_Categories" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Karst Feature Categories</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.) Also provided with the release version are three shapefiles having exactly the same information</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:normal;" translate="true">. </text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The only purpose of </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS Maps</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> and </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS TexBio</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> is the convenience (particularly right after an update) of being able to highlight with distinct symbols either the caves with images or the caves with TexBio fauna lists. The </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">TSS All_Types</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> shapefile contains everything, and is useful both as a backup and as a way to explore a table view of the entire database.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Normally the three redundant layers are set read-only (note the vertical bar prefixes) and their visibilities are turned off (boxes unchecked). That way we can&apos;t mistakenly update them or select their records in a text search. Although the records in these layers will become outdated as edits are made to the five essential shapefiles, I don&apos;t believe the extra effort required to keep them in agreement is justified, especially since one serves as a backup and all three can have their visibilities turned off as shown above. It&apos;s trivially easy for the data manager to create the extra layers with </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">TSS-Export</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">, so it makes sense to include them with each</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> new edition of the project.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Note that the bottom layer shown in this example is a georeferenced raster image (NTI file in this case) that users will have to obtain independently of the project download. That&apos;s also true for the DEM/DRG image groups. (See </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Available_Background_Imagery" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Available Background Imagery</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.) Regional data managers, for example, will likely have some combination of DOQs (aerial photos), DRGs (topo scans), &#160;and DEMs (elevation model NTI files) covering their areas of interest.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">With the project set up this way, it&apos;s easy to add new records and to edit existing records. To add a shelter, for example, just right-click the map view at the approximate location of the shelter and choose the appropriate shapefile</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> target. The possible targets presented will be</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> point shapefiles that are both visible and editable:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="AddShelter.jpg" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">T</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">he Selected Points dialog will open and from there you can refine the location and enter the appropriate attribute data. You&apos;ll notice that the TYPE, COUNTY, and QUADRANGLE fields will already be filled in and will update automatically as you tweak the location. If the location is within the extent of a loaded elevation model image, the ELEV_FT field will also be initialized. (The image doesn&apos;t have to be a visible layer.)</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Instructions for Entering Data</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">While table-style editing of attributes is possible, most record revisions are done via the form in the Selected Points dialog. In fact, all record additions and coordinate edits must be done using this dialog. Since the shapefile format limits field names to ten upper-case characters, the TSS shapefiles have custom templates that provide more information about what a field should contain. To access it let the mouse pointer hover over a field&apos;s label, either in the Selected Points window (shown here) or in a table view:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><image src="feature_help.png" scale="100.00%" styleclass="Image Caption"></image></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The custom templates also cause the automatic filling of fields COUNTY, TYPE, QUADRANGLE, and ELEV_FT. The initial value for TYPE will depend on the shapefile being edited. Filling of the others will depend on location, with elevations being obtained from an appropriate DEM image layer if one is present.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">Removing Records</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">To remove a record from the database, one does </text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">not</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> delete the record in the shapefile being edited. The convention we&apos;ve adopted for scheduling a removal is to simply edit the label field (NAME in this case), inserting an asterisk (*) as the first character. When the edited shapefile is processed by the database manager,</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> the corresponding record in the master database snapshot will be deleted and its TSS ID permanently retired.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
  </body>
</topic>
