<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<topic template="Default" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Accessing Walls from Other Applications</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Accessing Walls from Other Applications</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Walls currently has a </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="SearchOperations" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">search feature</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> that can perform a project-wide search for all occurrences of a string of characters, including those matching a </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="RegularExpressions" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">regular expression</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. The drawback is that you have to open each checked data file to see the context of any matches, or to perform replacements. On occasion you might need a search function that displays the context of all matches in one window, especially if you work with projects containing hundreds of data files.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">A shareware program that does this quite well is </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="weblink" href="http://www.wingrep.com/" target="_blank" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; text-decoration:underline; color:#0000ff;" translate="true">Windows Grep</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> ($30 to register). Upon a successful search it displays a list of file names and text fragments containing the matched phrases. (The number of surrounding lines that show context is selectable.) Furthermore, each matched phrase is a highlighted link that when clicked on executes another program via a configurable command line. The goal is to open and position the file in your favorite text editor. One problem you might find with Windows Grep is that the regular expression engine it uses is not very sophisticated. An alternative search tool that&apos;s much better in this respect is </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="weblink" href="http://www.powergrep.com/" target="_blank" style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; text-decoration:underline; color:#0000ff;" translate="true">PowerGrep</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> ($99). It supports the same kind of regular expression as Walls.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">To set up a program so that it opens a text file in the Walls editor, configure it so that it executes a command of the following form:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">C:\Walls\Walls32.exe &lt;pathname&gt; -L&lt;line number&gt; -C&lt;column number&gt;</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">&lt;pathname&gt; is the complete pathname of the text file, surrounded by quotes if it contains spaces. &lt;line number&gt; and &lt;column number&gt; are integers, with line and column numbering starting at 1. The better programs allow you to use special variables for line number and so forth when specifying the command line. For Windows Grep specifically you would enter the following under Options | Preferences | Editor Command Line:</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">C:Walls\Walls32.exe $F -L$L -C$C</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Although such a command will start Walls when necessary, it works particularly well when Walls is already running and has the appropriate project open. That way, when the file is opened and positioned in the editor, the program understands its relationship to the project. (One indicator of this is that the editor&apos;s window will have the same title as the corresponding project tree item.) From the editor&apos;s context menu you can then immediately follow links to compiled representations of the data you&apos;ve located.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
  </body>
</topic>
