<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" lasteditedby="David" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Instrument Corrections</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword translate="true">Instrument Corrections</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Instrument Corrections</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">INCD / INCA / INCAB / &#160;INCV / INCVB = &lt;tape/instrument correction&gt;</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Subheader" translate="true">INCH = &lt;height adjustment&gt;</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">The expression INCx=n, with n a decimal number and x one of D, A, AB, V, or VB, specifies a correction that the program will add to the corresponding measurement entry when it is processed. Those measurement entries are, respectively, Distance, Azimuth, Azimuth Backsight, Vertical angle, and Vertical angle Backsight. &#160;These corrections will be applied only to compass and tape (CT) data lines.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">&#32;</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Note that only the distance correction, INCD, will be applied to pure vertical shots, where the inclination is +90 or -90 degrees. &#160;Also, corrections are not applied to zero heights or distances, both of which are allowed. &#160;(Zero-length vectors can be defined.) &#160;However, if applying a correction to a distance would cause a change of sign, an error message is displayed.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">Like measurements on data lines, the correction units can be given explicitly with suffixes (e.g., IncA=1.35d). &#160;Otherwise, the units are assumed to be the current default for the corresponding measurement. &#160;In this case, if measurement units are later changed without a corresponding change in the correction, the correction keeps its original meaning. &#160;For example, a six-inch tape correction will stay six inches, even after switching to a meter tape. &#160;(This is done to be consistent -- &#160;we don&apos;t want some types of settings to be automatically zeroed when their units change.) </text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">The height adjustment, INCH, is a special case in that it is not an instrument correction, but a </text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; font-style:italic; color:#000000;" translate="true">vertical adjustment</text><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true"> that will be applied to all non-vertical shots. &#160;It is available to compensate for a possible systematic error in vertical target positioning -- something I&apos;ve personally encountered in a few highly interconnected surveys where techniques and personnel remained constant. Its default units are the same as that of the distance measurement. &#160;For example, &quot;INCH=0.04m&quot; would cause four centimeters to be added to the computed elevation of the TO station with respect to the FROM station. &#160;The mainframe program, Ellipse, actually provided a &quot;confidence interval&quot; for this height error as a product of the adjustment. &#160;Walls currently doesn&apos;t do this, but you can get the same result by trying out different INCH values while homing in to the smallest vertical UVE.</text></para>
    <para style="tabstops:24px left ;"></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text style="font-family:Arial; font-size:9pt; color:#000000;" translate="true">For an illustration of the effects of INCA and INCH corrections, see </text><link displaytype="text" defaultstyle="true" type="topiclink" href="Lot_Survey" styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Tree Survey Example</link><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.</text></para>
  </body>
</topic>
